This film is adapted from the novel of the same name
by Giuliano da Empoli.
Although inspired by historical events
it remains a work of art.
The characters, their words and opinions
and opinions, are fictitious.
Since Vadim Baranov
was no longer an advisor...
...of Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin,
the Tsar...
...the legends about him,
far from dying out, had multiplied.
Most men of power
derive their aura from their position.
When they lose it,
it's like pulling the plug.
Baranov was a different breed.
According to some, he had retired
in a monastery on Mount Athos.
Others swore they had seen him in Ibiza...
...surrounded by cocaine-addicted models.
Still others claimed
had spotted him on the Donbass front.
Vadim Baranov went through life
in a whirlwind of enigmas.
The only certainty
was his influence on the Tsar.
In fifteen years of service...
...he had made a decisive contribution
to extending his power.
He was known as the Kremlin Magus...
...the new Rasputin.
He barged into the President's office
in the middle of the night...
...to handle urgent matters.
Perhaps the Tsar himself
summoned him on his direct line.
Sometimes they were joined by
a prominent minister...
...or the boss
of a large state-owned company.
But these witnesses shed no light...
...the nocturnal activities of the Tsar
and his advisor.
When I returned to Moscow
a few years after his disappearance...
...the memory of Baranov
loomed like a shadow.
The press persisted in attributing...
...the Kremlin's
of the Kremlin.
As for me...
...my recent essay in Foreign Affairs
had created quite a stir.
It was entitled: "Vadim Baranov
and the invention of Fake Democracy".
If you need help, dial 9.
Good day, Mr Rowland.
-And to you.
I was on sabbatical from Yale...
...to write the first biography
of Yevgeny Zamiatin...
...great Russian writer...
...and early opponent
of Stalin's communist regime.
I was walking
in the winter's pallor...
...leafing through old books.
Zamiatin became my obsession.
He was a visionary.
Not just about Stalin,
but of all future dictators.
From Silicon Valley oligarchs
to China's one-party system.
From Mark Zuckerberg to Xi Jinping.
His dystopian novel, Nous...
...inspired George Orwell to write 1984.
Do people read Zamiatin
in American universities?
Zamiatin is the oracle of our time.
How long are you staying in Moscow?
I've got something to show you.
On the outskirts of town...
...endless, dark forests
stretched all the way to Siberia.
My curiosity was mingled with apprehension.
In Russia, things
generally go well.
But when they go wrong,
they go very wrong.
Hello.
Please follow me, Mr. Rowland.
May I take your coat?
I'll bring you some tea.
Do you collect old books?
I don't collect them, I read them.
Big difference.
Do you read Zamiatin?
I've got something to show you
you'll appreciate.
Do you know what it is?
A letter from Zamiatin to Stalin.
He asks her permission
to leave the USSR.
"Dear Iossif Vissarionovich.
"Just as the Christians
invented the devil...
"...to personify
all forms of evil...
"...the critics have made me
the devil of Soviet literature."
Zamiatine understood too much,
too quickly...
...and committed the imprudence of writing it.
Have a seat.
Have you read it?
-Of course I have.
You took the time to annotate it.
I'm flattered.
Let's not get carried away.
But unlike the others,
you've understood something.
Not much, but something.
Thank you.
Do you consider yourself an artist?
Let's just say I played a supporting role.
Now I'm retired.
Don't you miss the adrenaline?
There is no greater pleasure
than waking up in the morning...
...to have his coffee...
...and take her daughter to school.
How did the others take it?
My departure? Badly, of course.
At court, everything is forgiven:
thieves, murderers, traitors.
But not deserters.
"Don't you want what
we're willing to kill for?"
And the Tsar?
The Tsar is something else.
My father was afraid
of this library.
It belonged to my grandfather.
Custine, Gracián, Machiavelli...
...the skeptics, the disillusioned.
Not exactly Soviet doxa.
But to his credit,
he never tried to take it away from me.
Your father?
He ended up director of the
Academy of Social Sciences.
His only aim was to avoid
being awakened at dawn...
...by the KBG knocking on his door.
At his post,
he shouldn't have worried.
No one was safe
in the Soviet Union.
Nobody is in Russia, period.
Not me.
Not even you.
In my childhood...
...the most sought-after privilege
was the Kremliovka...
...a basket of victuals
reserved for apparatchiks.
What's for lunch today?
Pirojki with salmon...
...lamb chops.
Basically, my problem
is that I had a happy childhood.
In Russia, this is not normal.
The entire Russian elite
experienced Soviet misery...
...before reaching the villas
of the Côte d'Azur.
She still hasn't come back from it.
Even the Tsar:
"Me, the kid who grew up in a
kommunalka...
"...at the bottom of a filthy courtyard
of Saint Petersburg...
... "I've been received at Buckingham Palace!"
Things have changed.
-Well, not that much.
For you, money is everything.
In Russia, what counts
is proximity to power.
The Soviet system was based
privilege, not cash.
Yesterday there was none.
Tomorrow, who knows?
Might as well slam it shut right now.
Do you know what a vertushka is?
A phone without a dial...
...allowing Party pundits
to communicate directly with you.
Having one
was a sign of success.
Have a look. Here's a vertushka.
Gray, like everything Soviet.
If you find Moscow gray,
try Washington.
Over there, they're not gray,
they're dead.
In any case, I'm banned
in the USA and Europe.
Is your father still alive?
-No, he isn't.
In his world,
he could have survived for a long time.
But Gorbachev arrived
with his glass of milk.
His glass of milk?
You didn't have to listen to Gorbachev
to know that he would destroy the USSR.
All you had to do was look at him.
He would go up to the podium
and bring him a glass of milk.
Then he doubled the price of vodka...
...and tried
to put everyone on milk.
In Russia!
Can you believe it?
No wonder
that everything went to hell.
It was the end of communism
and my father.
He lost everything.
His job, his privileges,
his reputation.
And what about you?
What were you doing back then?
My father wanted me to be a diplomat.
But I didn't feel like studying.
I did odd jobs.
I used to sell TVs,
cassette players.
It worked well.
I started earning more
than my father, much more.
I was an ignorant kid.
That's why I was better adapted
to the new world.
THE NEW RUSSIANS
In the early 1990s...
...Moscow was an electric city.
There were a few brief years
full of hope.
Banned books
came out every week.
Solzhenitsyn, Pasternak, Bulgakov...
...Art and literature magazines
sold by the millions.
The Russians' appetite for freedom
was insatiable.
I enrolled
at the Moscow Academy of Dramatic Art...
...and I immersed myself
in the dissolute lives of theatergoers.
We were twenty years old
and a whole new world was opening up to us...
...just when
we had the strength to conquer it.
Open the door!
Open the door, bitch...
...or I'll blow you away!
We were too excited to sleep
more than three or four hours a night.
We were convinced
that our time had come...
...to rebuild society
on new foundations.
You could see pieces
from Europe...
...talk until dawn
with actors and directors.
Do you really think
that freedom will change everything...
...that you'll be living
in a world of culture and poetry?
Our generation has rejected the system.
Our parents bowed their heads, not us.
At the risk of displeasing you...
...communism was the reign
of culture and poetry.
How can you say that?
Under Communism, being a failure...
...was the only way to remain dignified.
At least we weren't making pacts.
Go away!
Go fuck yourself!
Perfect.
You've impressed me.
Really?
I wanted to tell you
because it rarely happens to me.
Interesting stuff.
You're not just anyone.
What impressed you?
-You did.
Your performance.
What performance?
Didn't you just sing?
You call that singing?
What do you call that?
Hip and trendy.
I did it as a favor.
To whom?
To the KGB agents watching us.
I'm delighted to give them
to spice up their relationships.
That's a shame.
You've got talent.
To do what New Yorkers
did 15 years ago?
You're a true Soviet.
You think the world
is waiting for you.
And you're not
a true Soviet?
My parents were poor fools.
Hippies.
They carried me
from community to community.
Today they are old, sick
and have lost faith in their values.
One thing's for sure,
I won't end up like them.
I have a role for you.
Will you take me seriously?
A role.
Like they do for actresses?
Just like they offer actresses.
Alas...
...I'm not an actress
and I have no desire to be one.
I'd go so far as to say
I've always done everything...
...not to be.
Do you know Yevgeny Zamiatin?
An icon of the avant-garde
the most conventional.
It's not my thing.
With all due respect, you're wrong.
I'll be staging his novel Nous
at the Institut d'art dramatique.
You take risks.
You're beginning to interest me.
Do you have a car?
-Yes, we do.
Take me home.
I've had enough of this evening.
In a hurry?
Am I going too fast for you?
I don't know how I make contact
with the planet Ksenia...
...but I knew at once that,
even if I were to live a thousand years...
...I would never meet
someone like her.
Everyone in starting position.
Scissors, D-503, in position.
What scene are we doing?
Always the same, Yuri.
The mirror scene.
Am I sitting or lying down?
You're lying down, and when you feel the light
of the Integral, you sit up.
Above all, be repetitive.
It was excellent, thank you.
Dinner was too casual.
Be more mechanical.
Is the Intégrale ready?
- Ready to go!
Keep up the good work...
...and when you feel
the light of the Integral...
...you all get up
and walk to the windows.
Milana, ready?
Yes !
An ugly case!
Clearly,
you've developed a soul.
Is it very serious, Doctor?
Inguérissable.
But what is it exactly?
I don't get it.
How to explain it?
Take a surface.
Here, this mirror.
You know that an ordinary mirror
reflects reality.
This one absorbs it...
...and keeps track of everything.
My brothers!
As you all know...
...over in the city, we're building
a spaceship: l'Intégrale.
Down with the Intégrale! Down with it!
My brothers.
L'Intégrale must belong to us.
And it will belong to us.
When for the first time
she will ascend to heaven...
...we'll be on board.
For we have with us
the Integral Builder.
He left town,
he came here with me...
...to be among you.
Long live the Builder!
His ambitions may have been vague...
...but Moscow's avant-garde theater
was unlikely to satisfy them.
I know. I lived those years in Moscow.
There were no limits.
Everything was collapsing and being rebuilt
at the same time.
It was fascinating and frightening at the same time.
Ksenia and I lived in a bubble...
...when life around us
overflowed with possibilities.
Every day, an old comrade
would come to me with an idea...
...a business to develop.
First on his grandfather's
his grandfather's bicycle...
...then in an armored Bentley,
surrounded by bodyguards.
That's more or less
what happened with Dmitry.
Sidorov?
-Sidorov, yes.
Dmitry Sidorov.
I'd known him in high school.
He was now head of the
the Young Communists at university.
Don't imagine an apparatchik.
In the late 1980s...
...the student cooperative
was the incubator of Russian capitalism.
I loved hearing about his adventures.
I wanted to write a play
about entrepreneurs like him.
Have you seen Dmitry?
Five minutes ago.
Try the bar.
A new social class,
out of nowhere.
It was quite astonishing.
Vadia!
Good to see you.
This café was my first business...
...but I used it to launch more lucrative
more lucrative activities.
Not all legal.
It's not legal anymore, forget it.
I'll tell you.
Stop writing. Just listen.
I'm your mom.
Once upon a time....
I recovered a stock of cognac.
Fake cognac.
-Fake, real, who cares?
I'm selling it for $50 a bottle.
Hear that?
Nothing. Nobody wants it.
I put them at $500,
we fight to buy them.
You didn't stop at cognac.
Computers, faded jeans,
souvenirs, software...
...thanks to the student cooperative.
A few little scams.
I find that hard to believe.
You can't fool her!
These are anecdotes
to entertain your audience.
It's a room.
I invented a trick...
...to facilitate payments
between state-owned companies.
I borrow money,
I advance it to others.
In fact, we call it
a bank, but...
...in this country,
who knows what a bank is?
Tough questions!
In fact, I created Russia's first
in Russia.
What was it?
I had found a book.
Commercial banks
of capitalist countries.
A remarkable work.
He described simply and in detail
the workings of the banking system.
I thought: not bad!
Would you say you're greedy?
Absolutely, yes.
I wasn't,
but I'm becoming more and more so.
That's an asset in my game.
I have a banker's personality.
I love money.
Nice suit.
-Nice shirt.
You've got some great reads!
They're a metro behind.
You still had your moustache.
Journalists are always a metro
late. You don't need me to tell you.
What a redneck mustache.
You were right to shave it.
How's your room coming along?
My play about you?
-Yes.
I won't write it.
-Why not?
It's over now.
You can't tell me the truth anymore.
You're right.
But I could never tell you everything.
Still, you were telling me a little more.
So, you're the famous Dmitry?
I can't think of any others.
Vadim says you weigh
80 million rubles a year.
Is it true?
-Maybe, I don't know.
He also says
you're a thug.
Really?
There's nothing wrong with that.
Ulysse Nardin.
A little too flashy to be elegant.
Flashy?
Says the girl with the bear on her head.
In my world, it's better to be flashy
than elegant to be respected.
Hence that horrible tie.
Eugenio Marinella from Naples, va bene!
Bellissima cravata.
Never heard of it.
Of course it is.
It's a tiny shop.
He travels
to make made-to-measure ties.
Custom-made ties?
In the world I live in, yes.
Do you like champagne?
Too flashy?
I should have known better. From that
meeting, my fate was sealed.
Ksenia would choose Dmitry...
...its vulgarity, its energy.
He felt it immediately.
And so am I.
But for a long time
I refused to believe it.
Yes ?
Coming, coming.
Is this a bad time?
I wanted to surprise you.
Hurry up!
Are you hungry?
Glitter galore!
Caviar!
From that moment on...
...Dmitry began
a regular visitor.
And here I thought
it was out of deference to art...
...to which Ksenia and I
had decided to devote our lives to.
As if culture
still had a hold on the real world.
I like that sound.
The flamboyant world of money
was Dmitry's natural environment.
Nothing could have distracted him.
But he wanted Ksenia, so he was willing
to linger with us...
...in the ruins of the City of the Dead.
As the months went by...
...Ksenia became increasingly sensitive
to his largesse.
Everything that had marked
the beginnings of our relationship...
...readings, concerts,
discussions until dawn...
...had given way to activities more
activities.
Gallery openings
and discotheques...
...dinners at White Sun or Ermitazh.
Ksenia was becoming more and more intoxicated
by Dmitry's lifestyle.
Vadia dances!
Vadia! Smile!
I'm smiling!
Communism is dead.
There's a whole new world to invent.
You'll be part of it.
Vadia, he doesn't like to go out.
All he likes
is to go home.
I remember waking up one night
and looking at her for a long time.
I felt so tired,
yet I hadn't done anything.
I had cultivated the illusion
that Ksenia would perceive my greatness.
But day after day...
...I noticed that the way
she saw me was changing.
What had taken the form of irony
turned into contempt.
"You're stronger than me
because you don't love me...."
I wanted to tell him.
My suffering
only increased his boredom.
Stop right there.
Stop right there!
Stop, damn it!
Would you like some water?
Dmitry, for the tenth time,
you drive too roughly.
There's nothing I can do about it.
Let Vadim drive
or I'll hitch a ride home.
Do you want to sit in the back?
You're cute, but I'm
sicker in the back.
I forgot to tell you something.
I'm listening.
I'm off.
Is that all it does for you?
You saw me with Dmitry.
You think I didn't notice?
It's been over between us for a long time.
Approach.
You're not bothering me.
I was afraid I'd wake you.
Have a seat.
I finally have an excuse
to stay in bed all day.
I reread the classics and doze off.
That's fine with me.
There's the disease.
It's going to seem paradoxical...
...but illness is not necessarily
a serious thing.
Serious business...
...like effort, work...
...are the burden of healthy
healthy people.
The dying have nothing left to do.
They can enjoy their days.
I left Ksenia.
I know.
You'll have a chance to remake your life.
I was expecting
to suffer a lot, but...
...I feel light. And strong.
You see.
Theater isn't enough for me anymore.
Losing Ksenia made me ambitious.
Are you ambitious now?
This is unexpected.
But I take it
as good news.
I can't stand the powerlessness
of the writer in the face of reality.
I want to be a player of my time...
...not just a witness.
You know what?
I leave your era to you.
And with no regrets.
This is Sputnik.
The only one allowed in here.
Come here, say hello.
My daughter loves it.
Finally, my father had a stroke
and died very quickly.
The ceremony
that the ceremony made the headlines.
Four clowns followed the hearse
in a dented car...
...overtaken in a hurry
by the SUVs of the nouveau riche.
He died too late.
He would probably have preferred
a nice funeral.
But in the end, he didn't care.
Well, I hope so.
I needed to take my mind off things...
...and Moscow in the mid-90s,
it was the ideal place.
Imagine all those young people...
...who suddenly saw the paths
before them the paths of the world.
They could become
whatever they wanted...
...make a fortune, cross the planet.
It was enough to make you lose your mind.
The level of violence was incredible.
Shots were fired from all sides
and for the most futile of reasons.
Private militias
escorted insignificant men...
...until one day
they jumped into the air.
Converting my theatrical experience
into a career as a TV producer...
...was like going from a cart
to the Lamborghini.
One day...
...I was talking about Mayakovsky
over a cup of tea.
The next day, I sipped a latte...
...in an open-space
designed by Dutch architects.
Forget the Première Chaîne,
forget state TV.
RTP is a private company.
We'll be playing games and politics.
But in a different way.
The Soviets tried to suffocate the country
the country under a blanket of boredom.
First rule: don't be boring.
There's one project above the rest.
It's this one.
Do you know why?
Because it contains
all the Russian stereotypes...
...without exception.
The provincial babushka...
...the nihilistic student...
...the ambitious little whore.
I read it. It sucks.
I've read them all, and they all suck.
-Especially this one.
Except that it will work.
We don't just produce
emissions.
All other institutions
collapsed.
It's up to TV to show the way.
A reality show about schools...
...where young girls are taught
to attract the nouveau riche?
Not bad. Does it really exist?
It really exists.
And it works like a charm.
My dream is to be
an international superstar.
My dream is to buy my mother
the most beautiful house in Krasnoyarsk.
My dream is to be the trophy wife...
...of Russia's richest oligarch...
...and live in Monte-Carlo.
She's the real deal.
Seriously, she rocks.
It's an excellent project...
...and this girl fits right in.
At that time, the RTP channel...
...belonged to a mathematician
billionaire, Boris Berezovsky.
He had bought an old palace
on Novokuznetskaya.
This should have been the headquarters
of his company...
...but Berezovsky made it
into something much more special.
A kind of club, the LogoVaz club.
It was a very select club.
The cream of politics,
business, entertainment and crime.
Imagine the scene.
We're in the Caucasus, in Chechnya.
I have before me a warlord...
...who took
Russian officers as hostages.
No kidding.
He's already decapitated one.
But it's not politics.
He wants money.
Right away.
I don't have any cash on me.
I don't carry around wads of cash.
But I can see he's eyeing my watch.
A Patek Philippe Nautilus
like this one.
So I said to him:
"Do you like my watch?
"You know what she's worth?
More than your hostages."
He says, "I know exactly
what it's worth. $800,000 used."
It blew my mind.
He knew the exact price.
Roustam was far from stupid.
He said to me:
"If you bring back the hostages...
.... "the publicity you'll get on TV
will be worth more than $800,000."
The soldier's stare.
Zero bullshit.
"You win. Do we have a deal?"
I give him my watch,
I bring back the hostages.
It was on all the news programs.
Back then,
my modest exploits as a TV producer...
...earned me the occasional invitation
to the LogoVaz club.
In general, Berezovsky would summon me
to discuss a project...
...or to recommend
a vague cousin...
...or an equally vague mistress.
Come in.
Vadia!
-Boris.
Our friend Vadia is a magician.
Thanks to him...
...we're wiping out the competition.
Do you want to leave it at that?
Not sure I understand.
In this country, you run the same risks
whether you're in the game or not.
I'll tell you my story...
...you'll understand.
I was quiet in my corner.
I'd built a modern, clean
business.
As far as I know,
your business wasn't that clean.
You recycled
stolen cars from the factory.
I was just like everyone else.
-Only worse.
You weren't very particular
about your partners.
I'm so sorry.
-Anyhow.
One day, some bastard shows up
and wants to steal my business.
What does he do?
He opens a competing company...
...to compete in the market
like in the USA or Europe?
No, that's not what he did.
This son of a bitch
loads up an old Opel from TNT...
...and the station on my way.
When I pass by, he presses
the remote control and boom.
No more Berezovsky.
At least, that was the plan.
Unfortunately for him, it didn't work.
I found myself with my driver's
in my arms.
I survived.
But that day, I realized
that if you don't take care of the power...
...power takes care of you.
I went to Switzerland for 15 days
for treatment.
And you know what I did
when I got back to Moscow?
You've learned to play tennis.
Not without difficulty. I hate this sport.
You hate all sports.
The old president, Boris Yeltsin,
was in decline.
Vodka abuse, they said.
He had built himself a sports club
on Sparrow Hill.
He spent his time playing tennis.
It was the only way to get close to him.
Let's face it, Boris was done for.
Elections soon,
his polls at rock bottom...
...All his little court of schemers
had them at zero.
They soon realized
that I was their only hope.
All was not lost.
Listen to me...
...Boris Nikolayevich.
Russia still needs you.
Your courage and your...
...integrity.
Nobody loves me anymore.
I saved democracy...
...but democracy here means...
...that everyone has become poor.
Except for a few smart guys like you...
...who picked up the tab.
If you give me...
...control of state television...
...I'll put together an election campaign
like we've never seen before.
Right now, you're in the hole.
In two months, you'll be on top.
That's how I took control
of the Première Chaîne, RTP.
But be careful.
I kept my word.
I resuscitated him in the polls.
Instead, you sank his rivals.
Nostalgic communists,
easy to get rid of.
You were defending your interests
and those of the oligarchs.
Yes.
That's right. And what's that?
That's the democratic process.
-Yes, it is.
According to a very vague conception
of democracy.
As meetings go by...
...the old man started to have fun.
Only problem:
...two weeks before the vote,
he gives us a heart attack.
It was hot.
The day he was to record
his final appeal to the nation.
Obviously, we cancelled everything.
But after a few days,
rumors began to circulate.
He had to show himself.
But the doctor refused
him to leave the house.
Too risky.
So we decided, as an illusion...
...to transport
the Kremlin's furniture to his home.
Flags on their stands.
The Federation on the left.
Watch out for the gap.
The Chairman descends.
Hello, Boris Nikolayevich!
Come and see what we've done.
It's a perfect copy
of your office in the Kremlin.
No one will know the difference.
Help him sit down.
Dear compatriots...
...which is why...
...the fatherland...
We'll be right back.
Misha, can you slow down the prompter?
One more time.
Dear compatriots...
...July 3rd...
...on election day...
...you don't...
...will vote not only for Yeltsin...
We're not going to make it.
Make her move her lips.
We'll edit bits and pieces
of his old speeches.
Yeltsin was re-elected with flying colors...
...then fell back into lethargy.
He suffered two further heart attacks.
During the 4 years of his 2nd term...
...Berezovsky was the real boss
of Russia.
The oligarchs scooped up
everything they could.
This is how my comrade
Dmitry Sidorov...
...has acquired a fossil fuel giant
for just 168 million.
It would earn him
3 billion a year.
Olya!
Berezovsky could feel the tide turning.
The Russians were tired
and needed order.
They had grown up in a homeland
and now found themselves in a supermarket.
The challenge was to find a solution
before someone else did.
So, yes.
I have friends in the Kremlin.
Sometimes I lend a hand.
But the scenario has changed completely.
It's no longer about
supporting the current regime.
You have to invent
something new.
Something and someone.
The President will not finish his term of office.
Someone to embody it.
That's easy.
But we need...
...first and foremost,
a party that brings everyone together.
The Unity Party.
What do you think, Vadia?
I already have an emblem.
The bear.
Symbol of the Russian soul.
You want in?
I don't know. I like my work.
I like my job.
It's the same job.
I'm simply proposing
to take it to the next level.
Stop making up stories...
...and invent reality.
With me.
LOUBIANKA
FSB Headquarters
The head of the FSB would make a good candidate.
The old man is confident.
He has proven himself
in decisive moments.
He's a modest man.
You'll like him.
Mr. Putin will see you now.
Enter.
Have a seat.
I know why you're here.
Of course you are.
You're the best-informed man in the country.
I've been thinking, Boris Abramovitch.
You see...
...secret services
have all the advantages of politics...
...without any of its drawbacks.
I'm at the center of the system here.
I'm well placed.
I can hear and see everything.
I can intervene effectively
to protect the President and his family.
I've done it before and I'll do it again.
If you take me from here
and put me in government...
...I'll end up crushed
like the other prime ministers...
...in recent years,
in recent months.
And you will lose
the state's most loyal guardian.
If we don't move fast...
...in a year's time there will be
no President or family to protect and...
...the first measure
of the new Kremlin boss...
...will be to replace you.
Why me?
I'm a civil servant.
Okay, I did...
...a few public speeches...
...but it was never stunning.
The President enters a room,
sniffs the air and everyone...
...is won over in two minutes,
laughing, crying...
...as if they were chatting
in his kitchen.
I'm not made of this wood.
If you don't mind me saying so,
Vladimir Vladimirovich...
...that's exactly what it's about.
The President's personality is unique.
His human qualities helped
our country...
...from the old Soviet Union
to today's Russia.
But it's worn out.
We need someone different...
...which marks a break with the past.
If the President
appoints you Prime Minister...
...you will embody a legitimate authority.
The Russians need
stability and security.
You're young, athletic and energetic.
Something inside you says:
"I can take full responsibility
of command."
Your career in the secret service
is a guarantee of reliability.
Being a man of few words
will work in your favor.
Not against you.
The Russians are tired
of salesmen.
The campaign we have in mind...
...will not be made of gatherings
and empty promises.
The challenge is to make you appear...
...as a politician
of a new type.
Vladimir Vladimirovich,
I don't know much about politics...
...but I do know a thing or two about
about communication.
There are two dimensions...
...in a company.
The horizontal axis is everyday life.
The vertical axis is authority.
Soviet society was vertical...
...and suddenly,
by ceasing to be Soviet...
...it has become horizontal.
Too much horizontality
means chaos.
Russians dream of verticality.
A psychoanalyst would say...
...that they are waiting for a leader
who will make them forget their mother's language...
...and once again imposes the father's word.
Public opinion quickly takes shape.
We only have a few months
to convince the Russian people...
...that you're the man for the job.
And don't forget,
you won't be alone.
I'll be at your side
to help and advise you...
...when you need it.
It's in the bag.
It's not a Nobel Prize in science,
but it'll do.
I nodded and laughed with him...
...but things
were more complicated...
...than Berezovsky perceived them.
When he addressed him
with his usual joviality...
...I perceived a shadow of annoyance
in Putin's eyes.
And there was this flash of irony...
...when Boris had promised
to guide him step by step.
As if the mere idea
of being guided by this man...
...was highly comical
in the eyes of the FSB chief.
Hurry up, Vadim Alexeyevich.
Vladimir Vladimirovich is waiting.
Good evening, sir.
What do you recommend?
We have excellent scallops...
...with cauliflower mousseline.
A bowl of kasha.
Two.
-Yes, sir.
I have great respect for Berezovsky.
I'm grateful to him...
...of his offer, but if...
...I embark...
...in this...
...adventure...
...I'll have to rely on my own strength...
...not someone else's.
The President of Russia cannot...
...nor shall...
...be submissive to anyone.
It's inconceivable to me.
Your analysis the other day
was very interesting...
...but first we need to
clarify one point.
If you accept my offer...
...you will work exclusively
for me...
...Vadim Alexeyevich.
I've been thinking about your concept
of verticality.
It's powerful.
But it can't remain abstract.
We need a well-defined stage
to restore vertical power.
Otherwise, we'll look unarmed...
...like all other politicians.
Indeed, Vladimir Vladimirovich...
...but snapping your fingers
snap your fingers.
Then there are the unexpected.
The unexpected is always
the result of incompetence.
It depends on the circumstances.
-Circumstances?
They're right in front of us.
Can't you see them?
Islamic fundamentalists.
They are no longer content
Chechnya.
They want Daguestan...
...Ingushetia, Bashkiria.
If we let them...
...in a few years, there will be nothing left
of the Russian Federation.
I'm sorry, but I'd think twice
before getting into this quagmire.
In recent years...
...Chechnya has killed
more political careers in Moscow...
...than enemies on the battlefield.
None of them put enough energy into it.
All these politicians
wanted to fight a war...
...that dared not speak its name.
A humanitarian war...
...like the Americans.
I'm talking about something else.
The Nobel Peace Prize
doesn't interest me.
What interests me...
...is to restore the integrity
of the Russian Federation.
I'm not talking about geopolitics.
That's not my game.
What I can say, however...
...is that politically,
it's suicide.
That's where you're wrong.
You design an election campaign
Western style:
...two teams of economists
discussing PowerPoint presentations.
In Russia...
...power...
...it's something else entirely.
That day, I didn't understand
exactly what Putin was insinuating...
...but I left that lunch
with one certainty:
Berezovsky had just made
the biggest mistake of his life.
The first days of August...
...Boris Yeltsin appointed a new
Prime Minister, unknown to most.
Vladimir Putin's appointment
was greeted with skepticism.
He was the 5th head of government
by Yeltsin in less than a year.
Our offices were located
in the former Palace of the Soviets...
...nicknamed the Russian White House.
A huge block of mothballs
on the banks of the Moskva.
A floor had been freed up
for new recruits.
Putin knew he had little time
to impose himself on public opinion.
He didn't intend to lose any.
Tell that son of a bitch...
...that the Prime Minister
wants results on the ground.
No matter how.
This is not media time,
but of politics.
We're here to produce results...
...not empty excuses.
I received your surveys.
Help me dissect them.
I'll join you in a moment.
I have to see Gusinsky.
We're on the right track.
Dmitri Anatolievitch, who cares?
...we should have arrived by now.
Where's Goussinski?
Unfortunately, he couldn't make it.
Aren't we important enough for him?
He's abroad.
-And you are? His messengers?
We run the chain.
Then you can tell Mr. Goussinski
the following:
The policy of the Russian Federation...
...is not defined
in the offices of NTV.
It wouldn't cross Mr. Goussinski's
of Mr. Goussinski.
I look at the Koukly...
...your political puppets.
Sometimes I think it's funny.
It makes me laugh.
Alas, the Prime Minister
doesn't share your sense of humor.
He suspects Mr. Goussinski
of trying to harm him.
But no, never in my life.
Too bad he's not here
to explain.
You represent the Prime Minister
as a dwarf.
This is not correct...
...A runt manipulated by the oligarchs.
In the minds of humorists,
it's more like a child.
Exactly.
And that's a laughing matter?
A childish midget?
It's a satirical show.
The Prime Minister defines
the line between satire and insult...
...especially at election time.
The Prime Minister
has defined a red line.
Mr. Goussinski can easily guess
where she is.
Otherwise, he'll learn the hard way.
Have a nice day!
I worked 18 hours a day,
meeting after meeting with the PM...
...each involving
historical decisions.
But the deeper I sank into the routine
of human government...
...the more the world
seemed full of misunderstandings...
...and missed opportunities.
Then the unexpected happened.
One autumn night, shortly after midnight...
...an enormous roar ripped through
the capital's darkness.
Guryanova Street,
on the outskirts of Moscow...
...hundreds of kilos of explosives...
...split a nine-storey
a nine-storey residential building.
Dozens of sleeping families...
...were engulfed by the explosion.
Four days later...
...a second explosion
shook the city at 5am...
...and destroyed another building
in the suburbs.
Over a hundred victims.
It was our September 11.
Until then, the war in Chechnya
seemed remote.
But when the buildings
started blowing up around Moscow...
...the Russians found themselves
with the war at home.
Of course...
...you know...
...what we say.
They say we've done it.
Finally, us: the FSB.
It's not just a rumor.
There are serious and corroborating clues.
Frankly, I don't know.
If this is a secret,
thank God nobody told me.
But why should we?
Our victory was a foregone conclusion.
To instill fear.
So that the Russians
feel threatened by the Chechens.
And to justify
the second Chechen war.
Which came at just the right time
to prepare opinion...
...to the arrival of an authoritarian regime.
I don't like expressing myself in public.
The people need to hear your voice.
Here, on a state visit,
not from the Kremlin.
Give them a sense of urgency.
I'm not an actor.
I'm just going to say
to a simple statement.
You would have ordered
to bomb Grozny airport...
...in response to the attacks.
You don't think that...
...risk aggravating the situation?
I'm tired of this kind of questioning.
We will strike terrorists
wherever they may be hiding.
If they're at an airport,
we'll hit the airport.
If they're in the can,
excuse my language...
...we'll shoot them
right down the shitter.
You have no idea of the impact
of that sentence...
...on the Russian public.
Finally, the voice of command
and control...
...that the Russians
had stopped hearing.
Stalin's voice?
Not Yeltsin's, in any case.
Nor Gorbachev's.
That day, Putin became the Tsar.
THE POWER VERTICAL
Mr. Prime Minister,
we can't land in Goudermes.
Visibility is insufficient.
I'm planning to spend New Year's Eve
with our troops.
We have to land.
We have to land!
We need 150 m of visibility.
We barely have 100.
It's too dangerous.
We have troops
stationed in Dagestan.
They're ready for review.
That might be an option.
If the Tsar wanted to ring in the New Year
in Chechnya...
...that's where we'd go.
At 1am, in jeeps,
we set off over the passes.
33rd Division, Lieutenant-Colonel Fedorov.
Welcome to the base, Mr. Putin.
Gentlemen, what you do
is very important.
People believe in you.
I'm here to tell you.
We're proud of you.
You work hard.
I know what you did,
it was very brave.
I want you to know
that the Russian people...
...thinking of you...
...and is proud of you.
Happy New Year.
Just a moment.
I'd like to drink to the wounded
and wish...
...a Happy New Year to all present...
...but we have serious tasks
ahead of us...
...as you all know.
We're not just fighting
for our honor and dignity...
...but to put an end
Russia's debacle.
We can't afford
a second's weakness.
If we let our guard down...
...those who died...
...will have died in vain.
So I suggest
that we put our glasses down.
We'll have a toast, but later.
I'm off.
I'm leaving before the end of my mandate.
I realized it was necessary.
Russia is to begin...
...this new millennium with
new political leaders...
...and I leave you in complete confidence...
...with Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin.
The Yeltsin era is over.
Your friend Berezovsky must understand...
...that I'm sick and tired
of these stupid memos.
I thought he was our friend.
Boris is a very intelligent man...
...but his intelligence doesn't protect him
from his stupidity.
Send him in.
Boris Abramovitch.
Approach.
Have a seat.
I read your messages...
...some of your memos.
You've always given good advice.
I'm all ears.
Volodia, you've kept me waiting an hour.
You wanted this interview.
This is it.
Go ahead.
I'll be brief.
We're becoming too negative.
Too dark.
It's war, we get it.
You're a great general...
...you will lead us to victory.
But let's make an effort.
Let's give a little hope
to these poor Russians.
Otherwise, instead of voting for you,
they'll throw themselves out the window.
Meetings, concerts...
...commercials and posters!
We need to make ourselves heard.
Who will pay?
-Me, of course.
Have you given up
free advertising space?
That's right.
It's a choice, our strategy.
We'll see if the facts prove us wrong.
If you keep this up,
people will forget you're a candidate.
Don't be ridiculous, Boris.
I've been acting president for 3 months.
We are the government.
Our campaign is the news,
what we do...
...the story we're writing.
Nobody believes in advertising anymore.
Facts are the only advertising
we're interested in.
The Tsar had restored
vertical power...
...and the voters
were grateful.
He was elected President
of the Russian Federation in the 1st round.
Berezovsky has stopped burdening the Kremlin
with unanswered calls.
Admittedly, his journalists mocked
the pomp and circumstance of the enthronement...
...but Boris expected something else:
...an opportunity to show the Tsar
who was in charge.
SOTCHI
Summer residence of Russian Presidents
I remember you prefer...
...just right.
Thank you for remembering.
Monsieur...
...On August 12, 2000, the Kursk...
...one of the largest
nuclear submarines...
...sank during an exercise
in the Barents Sea.
There were a hundred men on board.
Some died instantly.
Others were trapped
at the bottom of the sea.
This was the opportunity
Berezovsky had been waiting for.
We hired a helicopter
to monitor the wreck area.
Has she been identified?
-Yes, we have.
The news has just broken.
No rescue on site.
Outrageous.
This is what we must denounce.
Russian experts
refuse to get involved.
Look elsewhere.
We have a team in Germany.
NATO has offered to help...
...but the Russian navy refused.
These are spy ships.
Russia cannot humiliate itself
in front of them.
Can't humiliate himself in front of them?
Ask families
what they think.
That's what we do.
-TV is about emotion.
The emotion is the families.
Can you imagine their anguish?
Their loved ones, perhaps still alive,
locked in a watertight compartment...
...and the help that never comes!
How long will it take?
Our sons are paid $50 a month...
...and they're stuck
in this tin can!
What was the point of raising my son?
Do you have children?
Who can understand us?
Not you, the people in power.
You never understand anything!
All you think about is making money!
Our sailors don't have enough to live on
and you let them die!
The situation was out of control.
I rushed to Sochi.
I couldn't understand why Putin
wasn't there.
What do you want me to do?
They're all dead, obviously.
We'll know when we've reached them.
According to all the experts,
there are survivors.
It's a fact. We have to save them.
Dead or alive,
Berezovsky is out to get me.
Everyone's waiting for you to act.
I will act
when I see fit.
Your composure
has done much for your popularity...
...but it turns against you.
The Russian people are suffering
and you're not with them.
This is serious.
Since the authorities
still do nothing...
...RTP has organized a subscription
for the sailors' families.
Call this number to help...
Can you believe it?
They destroyed the state,
plundered it for ten years.
They've ruined our army
and they're organizing fundraisers!
All these bastards have to do is sell...
...their chalets in St. Moritz!
Call me that son of a bitch!
Do you realize what you're doing?
Your channel gives a voice
24 hours a day...
...to whores
playing sailors' wives.
What are you talking about?
You're delirious.
These are their real wives.
You're state television, Boris.
And you're plotting against the presidency.
What does it mean?
What does that mean, exactly?
I'm asking you a question!
I've got a question for you,
Vladimir Vladimirovich.
What the hell are you doing
vacationing on the Black Sea?
Shouldn't you be in Murmansk?
And where are you?
He laughs... Where are you?
On the French Riviera?
What the hell are you doing here?
Finally! I'm not the President.
Who cares where I am?
And I happen to be in Moscow.
Think, Volodya.
If you're going to console
the sailors' wives...
...you'll explode the ratings.
And our chain will put
all its firepower at your service.
And you know it's considerable.
What's up?
We're going back to Moscow.
We organize this fucking meeting.
We have no choice.
And as soon as we got out of that quagmire...
...we'll take care of your friend Boris.
How could Boris have imagined...
...that he would tolerate
a relationship of equals...
...with one of his subjects?
All the oligarchs were wrong.
By deciding to bet on Putin...
...they thought they were changing
the straw man, not the system.
Taking his television away from Berezovsky
was a piece of cake.
He didn't control the majority,
only 49%.
It was enough to inform
the general manager of RTP...
...that from now on,
he would take his orders from the Kremlin.
He means you no harm. He values you.
Stay quietly in Moscow
and do whatever business you want.
But forget politics.
Politics is his business.
Putin is a pure product of the KGB.
Of the fiercest kind.
He'll put Russia in irons.
And everything we've done in the last ten years
to become a normal country...
...will be swept away.
Even you, Vadia.
You're building a regime
worse than the USSR.
At least, back then...
...the Party muzzled
the KGB watchdogs.
Now the Party no longer exists.
The FSB is worse than the KGB.
Who's going to stop them? You?
I don't think so.
You've become one of them.
They're ferocious beasts.
They come from nothing.
They cut their way
with a sledgehammer.
No rules, no limits.
They're hungry.
An atavistic hunger.
They were humiliated.
They come from centuries of humiliation.
They have to take everything, right away.
Because they know the wheel is turning.
Maybe, Boris.
I don't know.
But I know that Russia
has always been like that.
With an axe.
UN HEADQUARTERS
New York
Cautiously,
Berezovsky chose exile in London.
In the meantime,
we were flying to New York.
When you reach the top...
...politics propels you
on the global stage without preparation.
The greats of this world
become your peers.
But they form a tight circle.
They had time to learn
the basic rules.
You may be feared and respected
in your country...
...here, you're just the new kid on the block.
The Waldorf Astoria is the best hotel.
Protocol has reserved a floor for us.
Twenty rooms.
Penthouse?
No.
Why?
The top three floors are reserved
by Saudis all year round.
It will take less than an hour.
15 min to get to the studio,
30 min interview and 15 min return.
It's a great coup for us.
What is it?
It's the freeze.
The US President's motorcade
is on the move.
No one else can move.
How long does it last?
It depends.
So, what's it like being a spy?
Not very different
from being a journalist.
We gather information,
we synthesize it...
...and present it to decision-makers
who can benefit from it.
Did you like doing that?
Intelligence has enabled me
to broaden my field of vision...
...to develop certain qualities...
...management skills.
Focus on priorities.
An apprenticeship.
The Kursk tragedy
tragedy moved the whole world.
Tell me, what happened?
What happened to the submarine?
It sank.
If the Martians...
...took power in Moscow...
...the USA would immediately recognize them
as a legitimate government...
...as long as they do not affect
their interests...
...and continue to treat them
as bosses.
The problem is that they believe
they've won the Cold War.
But the Soviet Union...
...hasn't lost it.
The Cold War ended
because we put an end to a dictatorship.
It's not the same thing.
We dissolved the Warsaw Pact.
We offered them peace...
...not surrender.
They should remember that.
From time to time.
Limonov thinks highly of you.
I thought he despised me.
He's a visionary.
Everyone has their place in their party.
So, what do you think
of my revolutionary avant-garde?
The Kremlin is not shaking
in its boots.
The Kremlin is wrong. Sit down.
So, how did the trip go?
You know what it's like there.
Still pretty fun, I'd say.
New York can be fun,
if you avoid Americans.
Which do you prefer, Édouard?
This one.
Have you been
to one of their society dinners?
All the men studied
Princeton or Yale.
Their children
go to the same schools.
At least younger...
...I could bang a little blonde wife
wife in the bathroom.
The discreet charm of the bourgeoisie.
It's the same everywhere.
No, Vadia.
America has destroyed the bourgeoisie.
The bourgeoisie had values.
These people believe
in numbers.
Boring as death.
The problem is not imperialism...
...it's American culture.
You were interested
before it swallowed you up and spat you out.
When I saw Yeltsin...
...turning Russia into a low-cost
low-cost version of the American hospice...
...I decided to found
the National-Bolshevik Party.
Do you know why
I called it that?
To enrage you!
Naz-Bol!
We bring together ex-Stalinists...
...homosexuals and punks...
...anarchists, skinheads...
...religious fanatics...
...from Buddhists to Orthodox.
The tricky part is preventing
from killing each other.
Trust them, it'll happen.
You don't understand.
These young people want to escape
the boredom of a humdrum life.
They are in search of heroism.
It would be a shame to spoil it.
Could you pass me a cigarette, Serguei?
I need to walk.
I'd always thought of Limonov
as a brilliant sociopath...
...completely devoid of political meaning.
I wasn't yet ready
to prove him right.
But his arguments appeared to me
for what they were.
Not the fruit
of rigorous analysis...
...but much more
than a hunch.
THE END OF THE OLIGARCHS
Vladimir Vladimirovich...
...Vadim Alexeyevich is here.
Enter.
How popular am I?
Elections are coming up.
Nothing to worry about.
Around 60%.
The next candidate tops out at 12%.
They are negligible.
There's a Russian more popular than me.
Stalin.
He's been dead for a while.
You intellectuals,
you denounce the horrors of the gulag.
According to you, Stalin was popular
despite the massacres. Not true.
He was popular because of the massacres.
Because he knew how to treat
a thief, a traitor.
You know what he did
when the Soviet trains...
...started to go off the rails?
-No, we haven't.
He had the director shot
for sabotage.
It didn't solve the problem,
it may have made it worse...
...but it gave the rage an outlet.
Rabies is a structural fact of life.
There's no point in fighting it,
just manage it.
Do you want to feed the rage?
-Yes, I do.
The people want a head.
Which one?
That of the most arrogant of oligarchs.
Dmitry Sidorov.
Your ex-friend.
I heard he stole your wife.
You should be happy.
It didn't last.
It's far from me.
He is preparing to sell the majority
of his oil company...
...to Exxon Mobil.
He's been working on it for a long time.
He will become
20 billion dollars...
...placing our fossil fuel giant under
under American control.
A Russian company would acquire
international stature.
No, it isn't.
He's building up a war chest
to face me in the 2007 elections.
How do you know?
-How do you think? It's bugged.
"Non-entity."
That's what he calls me
with his friends in Washington.
A "non-entity".
Or when he explains that once elected,
he will change the constitution...
...and dismantle our nuclear arsenal.
"Non-entity!
This man...
...made me eat more mud
than I can swallow.
I gave the order...
...to arrest Dmitry Sidorov...
...tomorrow at dawn.
He's on his way to Siberia.
He needs to refuel.
We'll pick it there.
Cameramen and journalists
will already be on site.
It's up to you to orchestrate
for the media.
This is it.
Here we are.
The news went round the world.
With the effect of reminding us
that money doesn't protect against everything.
For you Westerners,
it's an absolute taboo.
A politician arrested,
why not?
But a billionaire? Unthinkable.
Your company is founded
on the principle...
...that nothing surpasses money.
My job: to turn Dmitry's downfall
a successful TV show.
It wasn't difficult.
The masses have always loved
the head of a powerful man.
There is no dictator more bloodthirsty
than the people.
Once Sidorov was arrested...
...Putin's re-election
was a formality.
And so...
...the nature of Russian government
has changed profoundly.
The struggle for power
has left the public square...
...for the Tsar's entourage.
The state was once again dependent
on court intrigues.
There are those whose office
is close to the Tsar...
...and those on his direct line.
Those who accompany him abroad...
...and those going on vacation to Sochi.
No detail is too small,
no matter how small.
From table plan
to a gala dinner...
...to the waiting time
in the President's antechamber...
...nothing escapes
the courtier's vigilance.
I've adapted to the new regime
like I adapt to everything.
But others
were much better than me.
Like Igor Sechine?
Especially Igor Sechine.
Like many of his kind,
he drew strength from being underestimated.
When it came to courting,
he was in his element.
He was even the chief courtier.
With Dmitry Sidorov in prison...
...what to do with your company?
Sechine made short work of it.
Judicial sequestration, public auction
with only one participant...
...and it ends up in the hands
of such an opaque financial group...
...that he doesn't even have
phone number.
So, did you get what you wanted?
What the Tsar wanted.
He wanted Dmitry's box?
What he wants
is to destroy the oligarchs.
And replace them
by siloviki like you?
Russia has always needed
men of strength.
Military, spies, police.
That's why I'm here.
And that you take what you want.
Good for you.
If you want to put it that way,
Vadim Alexeyevich.
Be careful.
He returns from the G20 in Berlin.
Tired, in a bad mood.
It's always the same,
I'm treated like I'm...
...the President of Finland.
But watch out!
They'd better watch out.
The ability to inspire fear...
...is the poor man's only weapon
to preserve his dignity.
I learned it on the street.
Except that by scaring the enemy...
...we risk scaring the markets.
We can't afford it.
The markets
have never ruled Russia.
Maybe once.
Maybe once under Yeltsin.
And for what result?
The law of the jungle.
We need...
...to take control.
Control
of all the country's wealth.
Forests, mines,
gas, oil.
We will put them
to serve the interests...
...and the greatness of the Russian people.
Like with Dmitry.
-What, Dmitry?
The oil monopoly...
...went from Sidorov's pocket
to Sechin's pocket.
What does this have to do with the interests
and greatness of the Russian people?
It's a beautiful day.
You should go for a swim before you leave.
Thanks, but another time.
Do you prefer Sochi?
You know why I'm here.
I'd like to hear you say it.
-Rumor has it...
-You wouldn't come for a rumor.
According to reliable information...
...you are a fervent supporter
of the Ukrainian protesters.
Since you know...
-Putin is furious.
I was worried. As it turns out,
you're the bearer of good news.
Ukraine has been an integral part
of Russia for centuries.
Do you really believe that?
-I'm just the messenger.
You know what he said?
"Go see this asshole.
"Tell him he's out of line...
"...and try to reason with him."
Do you know what her problem is?
-I know what you think.
That he's not a politician,
but a KGB man, a spy.
He's not a spy.
A spy gathers accurate information.
He's a counter-spy.
His job is to be paranoid...
...to see conspiracies everywhere...
...to invent them if need be.
You've been in exile too long.
You're out.
As if those poor Ukrainians
had no reason to revolt...
...against a pro-Russian government.
Do you know who the main supporters
Ukrainian protesters?
The CIA, the US State Department...
...the great American foundations...
...you and George Soros...
...to the tune of $30 million...
...or so they say.
That's politics.
And you know what?
That's democracy.
You forgot the meaning of that word
long ago.
I'm not here by choice.
I live in exile, Vadia.
If I set foot in Russia,
I'll end up in Siberia, like Sidorov.
Boris...
...despite our differences,
the Tsar has kept his friendship for you.
You were able to sell your Russian assets.
1.3 billion, right?
They were worth much more.
And if I persist?
Will you send me killers?
Take a look. I have some, too.
And they're better than yours...
...because I pay ten times more for them.
I didn't come here to threaten you.
I understand your resentment.
But don't turn against your homeland.
Putin's Russia is not my homeland.
With all our faults...
...we had succeeded in building
a free country...
...where you could say and do
whatever we wanted.
A first in Russian history.
And you've screwed it up
in just a few years.
You have returned Russia
to what it has always been:
...a prison on a national scale.
Just like in Soviet times.
Is this your boat?
Nothing is ever mine.
Not in the sense that you mean.
At the expense of the oligarchs?
Are you scared?
Let your masters know?
My masters?
From what I hear...
...you put yourself at the service of power.
If you like.
You don't like
Vladimir Vladimirovich.
No. You're right.
I don't like power.
Especially when you tell yourself
that it's modern art.
I'm sorry, Vadia, but I think you're vile.
Naughty?
The word is strong.
-You deserve it.
You didn't answer my question.
We benefit from the money
from the oligarchs?
This boat belongs
to a Portland contractor.
He invented software at the age of 24.
Multimillionaire at 26.
Sold his company to Microsoft at the age of 28.
Since then, he's been bored out of his mind.
He'd like to have another idea
in his life...
...but it's a long time coming.
Are you sleeping with him?
Not at all.
When I have an idea for a jewelry line...
...it finances it.
Sometimes he earns a little money.
For him, cherry stems.
And he lends you his boat
whenever you feel like it?
Yes.
When the world bores me,
which is often...
...I've come to take refuge here.
A gilded cage.
Your comfort zone.
I loved Dmitry.
We had a great time for a few months.
I loved the craziness of the time.
And you dumped him, too.
I wasn't cruel.
Not this time.
We've grown apart.
Dmitry was interested in oil.
It didn't bring him any luck.
And for a few years,
I preferred Los Angeles...
...to the rest of the world.
Did Hollywood meet your requirements?
Hollywood!
I stayed away from Hollywood.
It's like Moscow.
The only thing that counts is power.
The rest is negligible.
I loved the desert.
I loved the ocean waves...
...driving on the Pacific Coast Highway.
And when I wanted to go to Japan,
I went to Japan.
This is my favorite cove.
Your plane is waiting.
Tonight, I'll be in Moscow.
How sad.
ORANGE REVOLUTION
MAÏDAN, INDEPENDENCE SQUARE
UKRAINE - 2004
The following autumn, as expected...
...the situation in Ukraine has degenerated.
The demonstrators refused
the election results.
By the hundreds of thousands,
they occupied the Maïdan...
...Kiev's main square,
with their songs, their orange ribbons...
...their colourful tents
and pro-Western slogans.
Don't spread yourself too thin.
Stay on the Maïdan!
Hundreds of thousands of Ukrainians
join us!
Suddenly,
international observers...
...came out of the woodwork
to contest the election results...
...won by the pro-Russian candidate,
Yanukovych.
These elections
were notoriously rigged.
I happened to be there.
Really?
We had just voted in Iraq.
American soldiers
controlled the polling stations...
...and everyone thought it was great.
But not in Ukraine.
No. In Ukraine, we had to vote again...
...because the result
was not the right one.
They called this farce
the "Orange Revolution".
The year before, in Georgia,
was the "Rose Revolution".
Another poetic revolution...
...pretty girls and noble ideals...
...but it's still
a vassal of the Americans...
...who is propelled to power.
Do you seriously think
a CIA conspiracy...
...so that the Ukrainian people
away from Russia...
...for the benefit of the European Union?
What people are you talking about?
Do you think everyone
finds your Europe so desirable?
You don't have to be a mind reader,
it's Russia's turn soon.
The next color revolution
will be in Moscow.
The future president
of the Russian Federation...
...will graduate from Yale.
The process seemed inescapable.
Youth couldn't take it anymore
and the Americans...
...exploited this revolt.
To survive,
we had to be stronger than they were.
The old methods
had run their course.
Arrest agitators,
expel diplomats.
And if we're in a bad mood,
liquidate opponents.
I don't believe in any of that.
So I took the risk
to adopt a different tactic.
The President has been informed of your arrival.
He sends his regards.
Alexander Sergeyevich...
...I've been following you for a few years now,
with your Wolves of the Night.
I'm impressed.
You take these losers and...
...you give them a home.
A discipline.
Our group brings them
two things they lack:
brotherhood and strength.
You're not just a bunch of bikers.
You are true Russian patriots.
We have values.
Russia's.
Those of our Holy Mother
the Orthodox Church.
I understand that, Alexander
Sergeyevich, and so did the President.
Wolves aren't just
predators...
...they are also the guardians of the forest.
Did you see what happened in Ukraine?
Yes. A revolution.
A coup d'état.
Do you know who took power?
The Americans.
-Bravo, bravo, bravo!
They created
a youth organization...
...financed free concerts
on the Maïdan.
I bet even the orange ribbon,
was the idea of a publicist.
Everything is tailor-made
for young people...
...because their energy
is the most precious commodity.
Their frustration...
...their desire to change the world.
Young people need a cause.
And an enemy.
You have to give them a cause
and an enemy...
...before they choose them
themselves.
Or worse, that Americans
choose them for themselves.
Except we can't do that.
Look around you, Alexandre.
Just bureaucrats in suits and ties.
We are the adults...
...we are the power.
We are their real enemy.
You're younger than me, I think.
You've taken a different path.
You embody freedom and adventure.
Your vital energy is intact.
Young people feel it.
The Tsar is with you.
He is your brother.
He's not a bureaucrat.
He likes speed,
he does judo, he hunts.
He's a conqueror's breed.
Do you think he'd come
to one of our gatherings?
Of course they would.
-The Wolves of the Night would be honored.
We're organizing a gathering
of young patriots.
We'll launch the fight
against the real enemy:
...the decadent West
and its false values.
The Maïdan, but in reverse.
Exactly.
Russia must become a place...
...where you can vent your rage
against the world...
...while remaining
a loyal servant of the Tsar.
In fact, you want to
to make revolution impossible.
Let's say we want to
abolish the need for it.
Without a drop of vodka...
...Zaldostanov left the Kremlin
in a state of drunkenness.
But he didn't know that after him...
...I received the intriguing spokeswoman
of an orthodox revival movement.
Then the leader of a particularly
Communist youth group.
And Spartak's fan leader.
I recruited them all:
...bikers and hooligans...
...anarchists and skinheads,
communists and religious fanatics...
...from the extreme right to the extreme left
and beyond.
After the events in Ukraine...
...we had to contain
the forces of rage.
The monopoly of power
was no longer enough...
...we needed a monopoly
of subversion.
Who didn't I hire?
The technocrats responsible
for the disasters of the 90s...
...the residual oligarchs...
...the standard-bearers
of political correctness...
...vegans...
...To tell the truth...
...I needed these characters
in opposition.
They were my best actors.
Virgin Mary, mother of God
Hunt Putin, hunt Putin!
Black cassock, gold epaulets
All parishioners on their knees!
The ghost of freedom is in the sky
Gay Pride sent to Siberia
When Pussy Riot took over
the Cathedral of Christ the Saviour...
...shouting obscenities
against Putin and Patriarch Kirill...
...we gained five points
in the polls.
I thought they were heroic.
They do it badly.
They score against their own side.
In politics, that's unforgivable.
It's a double-edged sword.
It made them world-famous.
Just a second, I'll be right back.
Vadim!
Miss Chekhova.
I'm very flattered to be honored
with your presence.
Don't make fun.
You're measuring the influence of your living room.
Darling...
...worldly chatter
has never influenced power.
Thanks to you,
I can rub shoulders with my rivals.
That's right.
Garry Kasparov is here.
Chess champions
never get far in politics.
Vadim Baranov.
The Kremlin mage.
-In person.
You've invented a name
for your doctrine.
Sovereign democracy.
Russia must be a democracy
to benefit from globalization.
I don't see any trace of democracy
in our company, but carry on.
Sovereignty is politically
synonymous with stability.
The more stable a system is,
the more competitive it is.
You know what they say
about your "sovereign democracy"?
That it belongs to democracy...
...what the electric chair
is to the chair.
It's just a good word,
but it's funny.
You've left the Côte d'Azur.
I never stay in one place for long.
You know how I am.
That's not one of my qualities.
Do you live in Moscow?
When I'm here,
I live in the Hotel Metropol.
I rent a suite by the year.
Is that an invitation?
You remember my friend,
the dog man?
Of course. Arseni.
He's a renowned director.
He has staged Monteverdi's L'Orfeo.
He transformed the theater
into a pagan basilica.
He calls it a space liturgy.
I was his high priestess in Paris.
Would you like to come along?
Unless that kind of provocation
doesn't interest you anymore.
Not sure I remember who you are.
I get lost in your labyrinths.
It's a game.
Politics is the only game
worth playing.
You've become a cynic.
You've reached the limit
of your intelligence.
Cynical.
It can be done.
But that's not all.
I don't know.
I'll let you know.
Right now, I'm not sure.
Come with me to the opera.
We'll have dinner at the Metropol.
I'm tired, Ksenia.
What?
To use your black magic
in the service of power?
The other day..,
I saw my reflection in the mirror...
...but it wasn't me...
...it was my father.
My father's face
printed on mine...
...despite my best efforts.
Let's go home.
I'm cold.
The last time I was here,
you asked me a question.
Do you remember?
You said you needed time.
Now I can answer.
You're not just cynical.
You chose...
...to marry your time.
You might as well have run away from him.
Do you like this weather?
-It's ours.
We're no better
or worse than him.
I don't blind myself.
I embody the worst of it.
And do you think you'll ever
to answer for it?
Do you believe in the future?
Not me.
The future doesn't give a shit about us.
"Our wound is raw
under the yoke of this time.
"See...
"...behind the forest where we walk...
"...trembling...
"...like an illuminated castle...
"...already evening awaits."
Rilke.
I'd forgotten.
I've never been fascinated
by Saint Petersburg.
It's a museum town,
petrified in time.
The Tsar, on the contrary,
is only fully at ease there...
...with his true lifelong friends...
...a mix of former FSB agents,
judo black belts
and genuine gangsters
who had hit the jackpot.
Both of them
seemed to have stepped out of Richard III.
In just a few years,
these obscure provincial schemers...
...had accumulated wealth
worthy of Gulf emirs.
Remarkable!
An enchantment.
All right, boys.
Our new chef's specialty:
...truffle risotto.
You tell me whether to keep it
or send it back to Italy.
Enjoy your meal.
Genia, we're disappointed in you.
You're serving truffle risotto.
Where's the arugula?
Need I remind you...
...that our ice hockey team
finished sixth in the championship?
We moved up seven places
in the standings...
...and overtook Dynamo Moscow.
Wait until next year.
You'll see.
Well, you'll get your rocket
next year.
No proper rockets in Russia.
But I bought an estate
on the Black Sea to grow it.
It will be beautiful,
but we have to be patient.
Keep the chief.
He knows his stuff.
His ticket to Pisa was already booked.
On Ryanair!
Yevgeny is very demanding.
But his talents go beyond cooking
to geopolitics.
Even to some of the questions
we're discussing.
It would be helpful if you could talk to each other.
I didn't know Prigojine very well.
Except as a restaurateur.
But Putin
had accompanied his rise...
...with unfailing benevolence.
A 5-minute flight.
Shortly after take-off...
...we began our descent
to Kamenny Island...
...where the Tsar's relatives...
...lived in the most beautiful palaces
of the imperial aristocracy.
I'm not an intellectual
like you...
...but I did learn
a few life lessons.
And not just in prison.
I don't doubt it.
You know how I got started?
With my partners...
...the first casino license
in St. Petersburg.
Or rather, the Tsar gave it to you
when he was deputy mayor.
Do you know what a casino is?
A monument to human irrationality.
Why throw your money away...
...when all the odds
are against you?
By betting on irrationality,
you always win.
Exactly.
Take an average guy.
As long as he's comfortable...
...that he has a secure job,
a family vacation by the sea...
...retirement on the horizon...
...he keeps quiet.
But if things go wrong...
...If he loses his job, his house...
...if the future becomes uncertain...
...will he play it safe?
Not at all.
He will choose risk
rather than the hopeless status quo.
Chaos becomes
more seductive than order.
The West
see China, India and Russia...
...make giant strides
while they stagnate.
They're willing to take the most
the most unreasonable.
Our job is to encourage them.
On the Internet.
It's the battlefield
of modern warfare.
I built the tool.
The Tsar wants you to take over.
Internet Research Agency.
I found the name.
Sounds good, doesn't it? What do you think?
Anton!
Our editorial director.
He has a doctorate
in international relations...
...and speaks every
language imaginable.
Nice to meet you, Anton.
Explain what you're doing here.
Influence. Information.
The Russian view of the West.
For the West.
They think their media
and their elites lie about everything.
They are customers
of alternative versions.
Our message:
We tell the truth.
Russia is telling the truth.
Like Russia Today.
We're on social networks,
not TV.
Would you like a coffee?
We have a relaxation area
with sofas, green plants...
And ping-pong tables.
Go ahead, we'll catch up.
Yevgeny, you'll have to explain...
...because I find it hard to understand.
Is something wrong?
Can we talk?
Of course you can.
I thought we were trying to influence
in Europe and the US...
...infiltrate people's minds.
And you're bringing me Anton?
He's the best.
-That's the problem.
Westerners
are no longer interested in politics.
To screw them, we have to talk
anything but politics.
We don't need Anton.
Whose, then?
-Idiots.
Quite addictive.
Otakus cyberaddicts...
...beauty advice bitches,
conspiracy youtubers...
...anything that generates clicks.
At some point,
we have to get our message across.
Who do you think we are?
The Comintern?
I regret to inform you
that the USSR no longer exists.
There is no longer a Party line,
no message to get across.
Only wire.
Come on, let's get out of here.
We're wasting our time here.
What wire are you talking about?
How do you break a wire?
You twist it one way,
then the other.
That's what we'll do, Yevgeny.
Explain how.
Build your network
and see who takes the bait.
They will all have an obsession.
The clicks will tell us what it is.
One will be anti-vax,
the other pro-life, or pro-choice.
We don't care.
We don't want to convert anyone.
Everyone just has to have
something that drives them crazy.
And someone who makes him mad.
It's foolproof.
No preference, no arguments.
Wire.
Twist it one way,
then the other, until it breaks.
I get it. The wire.
But everything is traceable on the Internet.
Sooner or later, we'll get caught.
Of course we do. And that's what we're looking for.
Supporting our allies is to be expected.
But how will they react
when they see
that we also support our opponents?
They'll think we're idiots.
They'll go crazy!
They'll be lost.
They'll just know
that we've gotten inside their heads
to tinker with their neural circuits.
The Americans created the algorithm.
We'll be using them too.
And better than them.
Those who accuse us of plotting
against democracy will be our allies.
They will build the myth
of our omnipotence.
This will be the greatest of secrets
shared by all:
...the Russians control the modern world.
They are the masters.
You see, that's what's interesting
in politics.
Anything that gives the illusion
of strength...
...really increases this strength.
LONDON
Borya.
-Vadia.
Are you carrying a message?
Sorry, Borya, no message.
So, in what honor...
...For pleasure.
Are you coming to meet
the British Olympic Association?
Always well informed.
The Tsar is now only interested
Olympic Games in Sochi.
The President asked me to supervise
the opening ceremony.
Are you planning to award the medal
for the best political assassination?
I don't know, Boris.
The main thing is that Russia
comes out on top.
I'm not worried.
You'll find...
...the worst solution.
As always.
You may not have
message for me, but...
...I have one for him.
It's okay, there's no polonium.
It's a letter to the Tsar.
It comes from the heart.
Read it if you like.
"I beg you to give me
your Christian forgiveness..."
Are you serious?
I appeal to his faith
and offer my services.
"Based on the experience
I have accumulated..."
Listen, frankly, no!
Times have changed.
You're out of the race.
Sorry to be cruel.
I appeal to his humanity.
Who are you kidding?
"The harshness of exile..."
"The passing of time..."
"The coming death..."
I understand.
But that won't make him blink.
The comfort of ending my days
in our motherland.
Can't he hear her?
I've got to go.
Give him the letter anyway.
I think it could work.
Sincerely.
I wish I could have told him
that it would work.
That the Tsar would be moved...
...that we'd find ourselves side by side
for the Olympics, in the grandstand.
I liked him.
Without being a saint,
he retained a childlike cheerfulness.
The Tsar having banished his own kind...
...all that remained in Moscow were the men
and their bleak determination.
Worst of all, I had contributed to it.
How did it go?
How could it?
He helped you.
You could reach out to him.
Boris sees the Sochi
the Sochi Olympic Games.
There's still money to be made...
...even if everyone
already lined their pockets.
Including you.
How do you like it? The main costumes
of the opening ceremony.
More importantly...
...did the British
the British Olympic Association?
Who cares?
They've already swallowed the Winter Olympics
in a seaside resort.
Devoid
sports infrastructure.
Have you seen the others?
No. Not really.
Take a look. Each island represents
a period in our history.
They're in motion,
they float in the air.
Our entire literary history
will scroll by.
The domes of Saint-Basile
will fly away.
And then
Swan Lake.
Do you like it?
Vadia, this Russia doesn't exist.
At least, not anymore.
But they're the ones who inspired us,
in the past.
It's too late for that.
You know it.
You won't save your soul.
This ceremony
is just a mask for dictatorship.
The rest
are empty pretexts.
I can see right through you.
That doesn't mean
that I don't love you.
But I won't be your accomplice.
Can I get you anything?
-Champagne.
Madame?
-The same.
The Tsar...
...will free our friend Dmitry.
Are you sure?
You've often told me that.
He will do so
two weeks before the Games.
The Western media
will have a field day.
That's the idea.
Aren't you going to ask me
what I did all day?
Not shopping.
That's not your style.
Something sharper.
Drop the irony.
I was trying to guess.
I was at the gynecologist.
I'm pregnant.
You look...
-I'm a little shocked, yes.
In fact, I'm overwhelmed.
I'm at a loss for words.
WAR IN CRIMEA
According to initial findings...
...hanging was the cause
of Boris Berezovsky's death.
Berezovsky was found dead
last night at his Ascot residence.
The medical examiner found
any signs of a struggle.
Access was denied
time to check...
...the absence of chemical,
or nuclear poison.
It was supposed to end like this.
He suffered from exile.
I'm going to miss him.
He gave a detestable image
of the opposition.
It was precious for us.
Here's the program
of the opening ceremony.
Updated according to your instructions.
What's Daft Punk?
Electronic music.
Number one in the world.
Two Frenchmen who never take
their robot helmets.
This table was not
in the previous version.
They've won five Grammy Awards.
It's time to get up to speed.
The police choir
will reprise their hit.
He turns the ceremony into a farce.
Explain your reasons to Igor.
This is what people
want to dance to. Simple as that.
It will be ridiculous.
It'll be kitsch.
The whole world,
three billion spectators...
...await the greatest show
ever seen.
It can only be
the apotheosis of kitsch.
Kitsch is the only possible language
if you want to communicate
with the masses.
We want to show them our Russia.
-Nobody wants to see your Russia.
Besides, you have nothing to show,
and everything to hide.
We want to give the image
of an open Russia...
...sure of herself,
but also able to smile.
Today's world
demands this self-mockery...
...not your balalaikas, Igor.
Do you understand what I'm saying
or is this just gibberish?
What do you...
...Vadia...
...is an acrobat.
Artists for politicians,
politics for artists.
Be careful, Vadia.
Sooner or later,
you risk missing the trapeze...
...and crush you to the ground.
I hereby declare...
...the 22nd Winter Olympics
Winter Games...
...open.
I probably should have left
that night.
Close the book at this page,
a good ending for me.
Ukrainian independence fighters
took advantage of the Olympic truce...
...to re-occupy Maïdan Square.
Two days before the end of the Games...
...they overthrew
pro-Russian president Yanukovych...
...who fled the same day.
The resulting chaos
gave the Tsar...
...a golden pretext
to invade Ukraine.
Russian snipers killed
more than a hundred demonstrators.
They say you're responsible.
Who says so?
Ukrainians.
According to your own e-mails.
You'd have Ukrainian blood
on your hands.
The day before the closing ceremony...
...following his grand design...
...the Tsar decided to annex Crimea.
Crimea was part of Ukraine.
We weren't going to send troops
invade a sovereign country.
You sent Russian soldiers
wearing no national insignia.
"Little green men,
said your journalist comrades.
When Zaldostanov
and his Night Wolves...
...landed in Crimea,
you were pulling the strings.
It's true, I did.
I gave them a supporting role.
Supporting roles are important.
As long as they don't get in over their heads.
Have you seen our flags?
We no longer use
from the Russian Federation.
We've got something else in mind.
We are no longer a federation.
We are conquerors.
We took back Crimea
from the Ukrainians.
Soon all of Donbass will be Russian.
It's time to take stock.
The point. Really.
I'm a man of action.
We're here to support the Russian army.
We'll bring you victory.
Who's talking victory?
Our objective in Ukraine
is not conquest.
It's chaos.
Ukrainians told each other...
...that their Orange Revolution
would bring them into Europe.
She'll take them back to the Middle Ages.
Western promises,
always end up the same.
They drop you at the first hurdle...
...and you remain alone
in your ruined country.
That's the moral of the story.
This war is not fought
in reality...
...but in the minds of the spectators...
...on the news.
Moscow, Kiev, Berlin.
You are the actors in a drama
that is beyond you...
...that resonates
far beyond these borders.
Or you accept to be a pawn
in my game, with all the advantages...
...or not. But know that I can
pull the plug any time I want.
And then things will get
more complicated for you...
...your Wolves and your business.
Who thrive...
...from what I hear.
May I disturb you for a moment,
Vadim Alexeyevich?
You're welcome.
How did your
your trip to Lugansk? How did it go?
You must have read
your department's reports.
We've heard from the Americans.
What news?
They would have established a black list...
...of undesirable personalities.
Your name is on it.
You'll have to forget about New York
for a while.
Sanctions for the annexation
of Crimea. When do they start?
Monday.
It's a good thing
I don't like New York anymore.
I also heard something else.
Go ahead.
It will be official tomorrow.
Your name is also
on the list of Europeans.
Paris...
...London...
...finished.
I'm told you'll miss Naples.
I'm not bothering you anymore,
Vadim Alexeyevich.
You have arrangements to make.
And fast.
Lionia, have you heard?
Yes, tonight or tomorrow at the latest.
No interview, just a press release.
Are you writing this down?
"I consider these sanctions
as an Oscar...
"...crowning my entire
of my political career.
"It means I've served my country
honorably." Period.
No, that's all.
Thank you.
Ksenia?
Pack your things.
I'll be there in 15 minutes.
A few hours later,
we landed in Stockholm...
...for our final European weekend.
I guess it was bound to happen.
It was up to you to avoid it.
By resigning?
For example.
Power is an addiction.
It's hard to wean yourself off.
Before, when you said those platitudes...
...I could hear the irony.
Not this time.
There weren't any.
The war in Ukraine,
is like everything else.
I didn't want it.
I even opposed it.
So you say.
That's right.
I'll say.
And I also say
that once the Tsar has decided...
...I did everything I could
to see her succeed.
Out of habit.
Pride.
And because I could.
No scruples whatsoever.
That's right.
It's been like that from the start.
With bombs from Moscow
and the war in Chechnya.
With the arrest of Dmitry
and Berezovsky's downfall.
And now,
the murders on the Maïdan.
I didn't want any of this...
...but each time,
I've devoted my tireless efforts to it.
And now you're tired.
Russia devoured my grandfather.
You knew my father,
she devoured him too.
I don't know if I'll be saved.
Probably not.
In any case, it's too late.
But our child will be saved.
Ksenia?
Ksenia!
I've never been to Novo-Ogariovo
with any joy.
The austere, sporty atmosphere
depressed me.
Once back from Stockholm,
I hardly ever set foot there again.
The trust of a prince
is not a privilege...
...but a conviction.
I had played my part,
I was no longer useful.
At some point,
he lost the habit of seeing me.
That's all there is to it.
He gets up early,
breakfast of fresh eggs...
...from Patriarch Kirill's farm.
This is where
he reads the confidential notes...
...and transmits its provisions.
Then
he swims a kilometer.
Its first visitors
are waiting by the pond.
Ministers, advisors,
business leaders.
The presidential motorcade does not set off
early afternoon.
The streets were closed
half an hour earlier.
From Novo-Ogariovo to the Kremlin,
Putin crosses his frozen capital.
And so begins his real day.
Sometimes ending at dawn.
One man doesn't sleep...
...and all those who matter in Moscow
share his vigil.
Just like in Stalin's time.
Who's this?
Hello, darling.
Can I play with Matchka?
Of course we are. You're not disturbing us.
Where is it?
What happened to Matchka?
Under the table?
-No, not under the table.
Not under the table?
-Not under the table.
Under the cushion?
-No, not under the cushion.
Are you sure?
-No, I'm not sure.
Is it under the piano?
-No, she isn't.
There she is!
-There she is!
All the happiness I've ever known
is concentrated in her.
Dad...
...what would Matchka say
if she could talk?
I think she'd say:
"I'd have more fun
with a real rabbit."
Daddy!
She would say:
"I love you more than anything, Anja.
"I only want to play with you."
Cats are not my passion.
But how long
can I make her happy?
I never knew fear before Anja.
Since the first time I saw her,
I've lived in terror.
My life is in his hands,
not the other way around.
My daughter doesn't count
hours or days.
I've always lived in the future.
She gave me the gift.
THE KREMLIN MAGICIAN
Based on the novel by
GIULIANO DA EMPOLI